Guide to the American Lutheran Church Women in World Mission Oral History Project / Evangelical Lutheran Church Women in Global Mission Oral History Project Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
American Lutheran Church Women in World Mission Oral History Project / Evangelical Lutheran Church Women in Global Mission Oral History Project Records
1920-1991
RG 100
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(5 boxes)
The American Lutheran Church Women in World Mission Oral History Project, and its continuation, the Evangelical Lutheran Church in America Women in Global Mission Oral History document the work of women missionaries serving under these church bodies (or predecessor bodies) from 1921-1991.; total linear footage This collection contains oral history transcripts of Lutheran women missionaries.
Evangelical Lutheran Church in America
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
The American Lutheran Church Women in World Mission Oral History Project, and its continuation, the Evangelical Lutheran Church in America Women in Global Mission Oral History Project, document the work of women missionaries serving under these church bodies (or predecessor bodies) from 1921-1991. The goals of the Women in World Mission Oral History Project were stated as follows:
(1) To preserve for future researchers the oral narratives of American Lutheran Church (and predecessor bodies) women whose participation in the church's world mission effort began, ended, or took place during the period of 1930 to 1980
(2) To provide a historical record of what it was like to be a woman in the missionary setting of the countries and period of the project
(3) To provide supplemental and historical data about the role and activities of missionaries in general, and women missionaries in particular, in the countries and period included in this study project.
Scope and Contents
I. Stage 1
II. Stage 2
III. Stage 3
IV Addendum
There were 247 potential narrators for the oral history project, a potential narrator being a woman (married or single) who served at least 10 years as a missionary between 1930 and 1980, in the countries covered by the project. The potential narrators were divided into three groups:
Stage I (38) Women born 1910 and earlier
Stage II (43) Women born 1911-1920
Stage III (166) Women born 1921 and later.
Of the potential narrators, sixty-three from Stages I and II were interviewed during the years 1985 to 1987. Countries of service represented by these women were Brazil, Cameroon, Central African Republic, Colombia, Hong Kong, India, Japan, Madagascar, Papua New Guinea, Nigeria, South Africa and Taiwan. The Evangelical Lutheran Church in America continued the project during the years 1990-1993, interviewing an additional thirty-four women. In order to accommodate important women representatives from predecessor churches not included in the American Lutheran Church project, the ELCA included some women born prior to 1930 in Stage III. Additional countries represented in Stage III include Argentina, Chile, Ethiopia, Guyana, Liberia, Nepal, and Tanzania. It should be noted that although China is listed as an area of service for several women, China was not officially included in these oral history projects; many Lutheran missionaries to China had already been interviewed by the Midwest China Center.
The Addendum contains oral histories of two of the directors of the world misison divisions of predecessor bodies of the Evangelical Lutheran Church: Theodore P. Fricke and Rolf A. Syrdal.
The oral transcripts are listed alphabetically by narrator within each stage. The listing also indicates country and dates of missionary service.
Information about copyright and permission to quote from the narratives is found in the introductory material preceding each transcript.
The Yale Divinity School Library's copy of this project is missing transcripts of two women present in the list provided for Stage II: Vera Eld and Frieda Foege.
Arrangement
I. Stage 1
II. Stage 2
III. Stage 3
Oral history; Women -- Missions; Missionaries; Evangelical Lutheran Church in America
- Stage 1, 1921-1970; Series I
  - Anderson, Adelia; China, Hong Kong, 1921-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bly, Stella, China; Taiwan, 1926-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boyum, Bernice;China, Japan, 1946-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burton, Laura; Cameroon, Central Africa, 1936-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Danielson, Helen; Colombia, 1939-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Eide, Emma; South Africa, Zimbabwe, 1938-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Erickson, Lenorah; Tanzania, 1940-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fliehler, Lydia; Papua New Guinea, 1930-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hallanger, Alvilde; Madagascar, 1928-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Helland, Muriel; India, 1926-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hennum, Gunda; Madagascar, 1937-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hoeger, Agnes; Papua New Guinea, 1935-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jensen, Cornelia; Colombia, 1959-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kettner, Gertruth; India, 1937-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kuder, Louise; Papua New Guinea, 1934-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Larson, Pearl; Cameroon, 1936-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lovaas, Alta; Madagascar, 1924-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mager, Alice; Papua New Guinea, 1937-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Matthias, Erma; Papua New Guinea, 1947-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Nelson, Doris; South Africa, 1929-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Norlie, Solveig; Madagascar, 1937-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Nybroten, Magnhild; Madagascar, 1936-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Olson, Opal; Colombia, 1944-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Rindahl, Laura; South Africa, 1930-1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Thompson, Milla; Madagascar, 1954-1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Vaagenes, Hanna; Madagascar, 1920-1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Winther, Maya; Papua New Guinea, 1928-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Stage 2, 1951-1968; Series II
  - Aamodt, Elvira; Japan, 1951-1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Arnston, Norma; Papua New Guinea, 1963-1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Brandt, Amee; Papua New Guinea, 1945-1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bergh, Joyce; Colombia, 1947-1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ditmanson, Joyce; Taiwan, 1957-1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Eastvold, Alice; Cameroon, (n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Frerichs, Sylvia; Papua New Guinea, 1946-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hall, Margaret; South Africa, 1952-1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hanse, Eleanor Japan, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hyland, Judy; Japan, 1940-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jacobsen, Helen Margaret; Nigeria, 1942-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Johnson, Camilla; Madagascar, 1948-1976 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Johnson, Caroline; Madagascar, 1946-1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Johnsrud, Carolyn; Japan, 1950-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Kjome, June; South Africa, 1945-1964 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Knutson, Judith; Madagascar, 1947-1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Larsen, Florence; Cameroon, 1950-1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Lee, Kathryn Brazil, 1958-1968 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Lovaas, Evelyn; Madagascar, 1946-1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Mild, Frieda Papua New Guinea, 1936-1958 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Mitchell, Anna Marie Japan, 1950-1982 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Monke, Mildred; India, 1938-1961 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Morck, Hildur; Colombia, 1946-1976 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Nissen, Margaretha Nigeria, 1943-1975 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Olson, Mellie Japan, 1951-1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Pedersen, Lois; Japan, 1950-1975 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Rossing, Anna; Madagascar, 1937-1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Sand, Beryl; Cameroon, 1943-1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Scherle, Edna; Papua New Guinea, 1946-1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Sherer, Ruth; Papua New Guinea, 1946-1960 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Smith, Margaret; Central African Republic, 1953-1983 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Stovner, Harriet; Cameroon, 1947-1979 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Tang, Cleone; Japan, 1950-1968 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Winter, Theora; Papua New Guinea, 1947-1969 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Stage 3, 1952-1977; Series III
  - Brown, Della; Tanzania, 1952-1977 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Coleman, Margaret; India, 1939-1983 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Ehrhart, Miriam; Liberia, 1954-1966 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Erickson, Helen; Tanzania, 1944-1983 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Faust, Louise;Tanzania, 1949-1975 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Halvorson, Marian; Tanzania, 1946-1977 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Hansen, Ruth; Guyana, 1948-1982 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Jacobsen, Evelyn; Madagascar, 1955-1990 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Johansson, Alice; Nepal, Tanzania, 1954-1965 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Knutson, Arlene; South Africa, 1954-1972 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Leidenfrost, Jane; Liberia, 1956-1989 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Miller, Margaret; Liberia, 1954-1987 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Nelson, Evelyn; China, Hong Kong, 1944-1984 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Nelson, Irene; Japan, 1952-1991 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Neudoerffer, Theodora; India, 1935-1976 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Neve, Muriel; Japan, 1948-1988 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Olson, Louise; Tanzania, 1946-1989 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Olson, Miriam; Japan, 1950-1990 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Peery, Marinelle; India, 1947-1988 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Sadler, Roslyn; Indonesia, Liberia, Rhodesia, 1940-1978 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Sanoden, Alice; Japan, 1952-1989 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Schaeffer, Trudy; Ethiopia, Hong Kong, India, 1955-1989 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Schaffer, Elizabeth Liberia, 1959-1974 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Sigmon, Ruth; India, 1945-1988 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Slifer, Ruth; India, 1948-1980 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Solvik, Clarice; Liberia, Nepal, 1949-1964 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Spehr, Lydia; Liberia, 1964-1990 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Tack, Minnie; China, Hong Kong, 1921-1968 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Townsend, Virginia; Argentina, 1949-1967 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Wagner, Elaine; Guyana, 1947-1983 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Walck, Marion; Papua New Guinea, 1947-1972 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Wangen, Dorothy; Brazil, 1956-1991 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Wilke, Myrtle; China, Peru, 1927-1973 (Box 5, Folder 48)
- Addendum, 1994; Series IV
  - Oral histories of directors of world mission divisions: Theodore P. Fricke and Rolf A. Syrdal, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 49)